[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchali my guest
today is noah gift and we'll be talking
about ml ops nova gift is an executive
in residence at the duke m ids data
science and ai product innovation
programs and teaches ml ops data
engineering cloud computing and
solopreneurship he is the author of
multiple technical publications
including recent books practical ml ops
which this episode will get into python
for devops among others
noah is also the founder of pragmatic ai
labs which develops technical content
around mlaps devops data science and
cloud computing noah welcome to the show
hi happy to be here so to set the
context for rest of our episode can you
briefly describe
what is ml ops
yeah i would describe emalops as
a combination of four different
items
one would be devops i would say that's
about 25 of it
the other 25
would be data engineering or data ops
the other 25 would be modeling so things
like you do on kaggle and then the other
would be
business so you know product management
essentially knowing what it is you're
solving
i would describe it as a combination of
those four things
and how do you see that differing from
devops in general because you said
devops was like a part of it so where's
the difference beyond devops there yeah
so in terms of devops really the concept
is fairly straightforward it's the idea
of automating your software
infrastructure
so that you're able to rapidly release
changes you're building evolutionary
architecture
and you're you know be able to use the
cloud for example to do
infrastructure as code and to use
virtualization so really it's the idea
of having a iterative agile
environment where there are
very few manual components and i think
many organizations understand that and
they're doing devops i mean it took a
while for organizations to fully adopt
it but many people are doing this but in
terms of machine learning operations
there's a few wild cards here
and
one of them is that if you don't have
data it's going to be very difficult to
do machine learning operations so you
you need to have some kind of a pipeline
for data
and i would compare this a lot like the
water system in a city
where you can't have a dishwasher or a
washing machine or a swimming pool
if you don't have water hookup and
treatment plants where once the water
has been
you know something's been done with it
you're able to process it and if you
don't have that data pipeline set up
you're not going to be able to do mlaps
and then likewise
what's a little bit different versus
devops is that there are new new things
so
if it's just devops you know you you
could be i don't know deploying mobile
applications
and there are some interesting things
about that but it's it's fairly well
known now but with machine learning
you're going to deal with things like
models and the models could introduce
another
basically component that has to be
watched so for example
you know is the model accurately
performing
in production
has the data
changed a lot since the last time you
train the model
and so you have to add new
characteristics so in some sense there's
a lot of similarity to to devops but the
main thing is that there's new
components
that have to be treated
in a similar fashion as what you've done
in the past i i think in some sense like
going from web development to mobile
development there could be some
similarity there and that
if anyone remembers when you first got
into web development there's kind of the
classic things of
there's javascript and html and a
relational database but then when you
get into mobile it's like oh wow there's
a new thing now we have to you know do
swift code or objective c code or we
have to use android
and then you know i have to deal with
different things like how do i deploy my
my mobile device and so in some sense
it's just another component but it has
to be treated in a unique way
that the properties of that component
have to be respected and taken care of
and that they're a little bit different
just like web development has some
similarity to mobile development but
it's not the same there are some very
unique differences
right in your book you talk about
reaching the true potential of machine
learning is dependent on
a couple of fundamental things being
present already and you compare this
with mass loss hierarchy of needs in
order for humans or anyone to reach full
potential you know you need food water
safety and so on up until like the full
potential is really at the top of that
pyramid so to speak so what is this
hierarchy of needs for machine learning
to be successful were those layers that
build on to a successful machine
learning organization or product yeah so
i would say to start with the
foundational layer is devops
and
you know i think
if
your company is already
in the software space doing let's say
software as a service
it's very likely that your company has
very strong devops capabilities for one
you probably won't you wouldn't have
survived if you didn't have devops
capabilities you know when i was first
working in the software industry in the
bay area
many of the companies i went to did not
have devops and that's what i helped
them implement
and it really is a big problem to not
have devops now if you're in the
data science world or coming from
academics devops may be something you
really don't have any familiarity with
and so in that scenario if you're at a
startup and everybody is just from
university and they're used to using
jupyter notebooks they could be in for a
rude surprise
in the fact that they need to implement
devops and you know devops again
automation testing continuous
integration continuous delivery
you know using cloud computing using
microservices
if you don't have those capabilities
already in your organization you're
really going to need to build those so
that is the foundational layer
as i mentioned depends on where you're
coming from you may already have it now
the next layer would be now if you're a
software engineering shop it's possible
that even though you're really good at
software engineering
you may not be good at the next layer
which would be the data engineering so
building a data pipeline and so now you
may need to build a new capability and
the new capability would be to
move the data into the locations that
needs to move
make sure that you're able to
automatically handle
different processes that prepare the
data for machine learning
i think what we're seeing right now
in the mlap space is that many
organizations are using something called
a feature store
and that's a data engineering best
practice for mlaps and many companies
are now coming out with platforms that
have feature stores
i know that snowflake which is a big
data management tool that's publicly
traded they have implemented a feature
store by buying a company that had that
capability i know databricks 10 billion
dollar company they just implemented a
feature store sagemaker one of the
biggest mlaps platforms they've entered
you know used the feature store
iguazio is a company that i'm an advisor
to they use a feature store so so
basically that's that's the next
evolution is use the right tools for the
job use data management processes
you know use the the new systems that
are being developed
assuming you have that then the next
layer up would be the platform
automation
and this is where i think it's very easy
for the data scientists to get
themselves into trouble
where maybe the software engineer
would be a little better at
understanding that yeah you do need to
use a platform like if you take the
c-sharp developer
who has been developing.net for 10 years
or 20 years
they understand you need a platform they
have visual studio they have net they
have all these like really awesome tools
and like why would they not use all
those tools they make them more
productive
and similarly with doing things in
machine learning my recommendation is
that somebody picks a platform of some
kind it could be sage maker for aws it
could be azure ml studio
for azure it could be databricks if you
want to do spark based systems whatever
it is you're deciding to pick i'm more
neutral on this but you should use some
platforms so that you can focus on
solving holistically the whole problem
versus building out orchestration
systems and distributed computing
systems and monitoring systems and all
these things that have nothing to do
with mlaps
by itself
so once you've got all that
and you are using some platform then at
that point i do believe you're at the
stage where mlops is possible
the one
last step though would be that
you need to make sure that there's a
good feedback loop with the stakeholders
in your organization like the product
managers the ceo so that you're able to
formulate what it is you're trying to
build so in this sense it's not that
different than
regular software engineering you know
i've made a lot of new products in my
life and one of the things that's really
critical is to work with the product
managers to make sure that the thing
you're building actually makes sense
like is there roi can it make money can
it solve problems for customers so
similarly even though you can build
something just because you have the
capabilities and you've done all the
steps doesn't mean necessarily you
should without doing a little bit of due
diligence but yeah that would be the
foundation
yeah and i think when you mentioned
feature stores i want to add to our
listeners we did a recent episode on
feature source i'll leave a link to that
in the show notes if you want to go and
listen to that but continuing on with
what you were saying
there's a lot of different people
involved in machine learning that you
don't normally see at in just
traditional software traditional
software shop that has some sort of
devops thing in place
for example maybe you are working in a
product that is in the healthcare space
and you're working with say radiologists
who are reading
x-rays and they're contributing to your
machine learning model or how you go
about building machine learning so what
are the challenges that that sort of
like different people with different
skill sets different backgrounds uh
coming in to build
machine learning applications what are
the kind of challenges that you run into
when you have these diverse set of
people working on machine learning
products which
i think is increasingly common
yeah i think one of the problems is that
there needs to be a production first
mindset
and that alone could solve a lot of
issues so if from the very beginning
you're using version control you're
using continuous integration you're
using a platform i think all of those
are some of the ways to to add
guardrails to the process if from the
very beginning you have some people that
have phds and they're in the corner
working with jupiter notebook and then
you have some other people that are
doing devops and using infrastructure as
code then that definitely is going to
cause a conflict at some point
it really has to be from the very
beginning that you're using this
production first mindset now we're
seeing this actually with a lot of
the evolution of the tooling and i know
sagemaker i was just reading today in
fact that they have with this whole
concept of sagemaker projects and you
build out the whole project as like
like a machine learning software
engineering project so i think those are
some of the things that that would go a
long way is is making sure that you're
treating it like you would treat
holistically something that's going to
go to production so like no one that's a
software engineer would basically just
start i mean if you're really a beginner
and you've never had any experience you
would just start writing code without
version control or tests or anything
like that or or like a you know some
kind of editor
but if you're a professional you
wouldn't you would never do that you
would make sure that it was hooked up
and you could continuously deploy your
software so similarly from the very
beginning you should not make a mess you
should build out a production first
mindset
yeah can you comment a little more about
the continuous integration aspect of it
i know there's various layers in terms
of say how your data interacts with it
but just in terms of just the model
which changes over time it might be a
statistical representation of signals
that you've trained in the past and now
you want to continuously improve maybe
you want to go back to some version of
the model so how is that represented how
do you have version control
and continuous integration on models
itself
i would say the software part
you know is the part that i would say
the continuous integration even though
it's a machine learning product
it doesn't mean that the software went
away so the software still has to be
tested and you still have to have
linting and things like that so that's
where i was more referring to the
continuous integration is that
regardless there'll be some microservice
that's going to you know be built and
it'll have to have a model in there now
the stuff you bring up about the model
versioning well in that case you know i
think the scenario would be that
you would
just like you would with
any other kind of versioning system like
a python package you would pin the model
version
alongside the microservice maybe build
out a docker container and then
potentially do some kind of integration
test before you put that into production
that's probably the approach i would use
which is you would merge this you know
pin the version number for the libraries
pin the version number for the model
and even maybe even version the data pin
the version number and then push that
into let's say a staging branch by
merging from the development brand to
the stadium branch
going through and then doing some kind
of maybe a load test to verify that
inference works at scale and then also
doing some kind of performance test that
says okay here's the accuracy would we
would expect with you know some
validation data so you can do some of
the same things that you would do
with a regular software engineering
project
but the functional tests are are
slightly different
just in the fact that they're they're
also validating
the accuracy of the of the model when it
goes into production which which isn't
that dissimilar than you know some some
tests that would test the business logic
data is really at the center of the
model itself like you have data that's
present to the company that access input
signals maybe there's data based on your
interaction right now that comes into
your model as an input signal
how do you reproduce your tests when i i
built some sort of model right now and i
think the accuracy for that is say 60
that depends on having some static data
right now and
that underlying data might change over
time
so in the ml ops world how do you plan
for
keeping tests that are
reproducible that you can actually rely
on over time as you
change things with respect to say the
data of pipelines or even with respect
to the model representation
i think there's a lot of different ways
that you could do that one is that you
could do data drift detection so
if the last time you trained your model
the data had maybe drifted more than 10
then potentially what you would do is
just automatically trigger a new build
of the model and then you could do your
your integration test
that verified that the model performance
with the new trained model still worked
pretty well in addition to that you
could also
and i think this is more of a newer
style which is you could keep version
copies of your data so if you are using
let's say a feature store for example
that would be much easier to
to do data versioning with right because
you're actually versioning the features
and then you could say well at this
point in time this is what our accuracy
was let's go to the new version of the
of the features and then let's train a
new model and see is this better
you know and then you could even go back
and you could mix and match so so i
think this is where the iteration of
i think the feature store really could
be a very interesting you know component
to a pipeline where you're sifting the
data
to the point where
it becomes more
more like something that that you would
keep in a versioned manner so that you
can do things like retrain rapidly and
verify that the accuracy
is still good enough
what are some
reasons why your accuracy might go down
over time do you have any examples maybe
you know one example i had when i was
working
at a sports social media company that i
was the cto at we
initially were this was 2013
and it's it's actually amazing how much
the world has changed with social media
in the last 10 years but a lot of the
issues that we're seeing today actually
we we saw in social media at the time
like one of the issues is
is actually who is influential
and we're you know like i think a couple
days ago elon musk was saying are there
bots on twitter like who's really
you know got followers you know these
are questions that we were dealing with
10 years ago and
one of the things that we discovered was
that the engagement relative engagement
was one of the stronger signals for
basically influence and
what we did was we trained models
that would look at the relative
engagement
but when we initially were training our
models to figure out who to partner with
and which was one of the machine
learning jobs that i developed initially
we didn't have a ton of data because
in order for us to figure out the signal
we needed to
first capture their relative engagement
on multiple social media platforms
twitter facebook and even we used
wikipedia for this
in addition to that we also needed to
have actual data
and so it's the whole cold start problem
so once they posted content onto our
platform
then we were able to get some data but
if we didn't have the data we had
you know essentially a very very small
data set and that's a perfect example
where when i first created the model
it was a lot different than the model
when there's a lot of data because
which is you know now it's pretty
intuitive to everybody but basically
there's a massive
exponential relationship
you know between
somebody who's just a regular person and
let's say
you know ronaldo or something like that
i mean they they're or beyonce or
something like they're so far
you know above that
there needs to be like a power law you
know relationship and so you know if
you're initially your model is
predicting let's say more of a linear
relationship
because you just don't have a lot of
data
and you just kept staying with that then
you know that could be a real problem
because your accuracy is going to be
very very different as more and more
data kind of populates in so that's a
perfect example of the data drift
problem is is that hey we for the first
amount of people maybe were they weren't
like huge influencers the model was okay
but then all of a sudden as we start to
get some of these like superstars that
came into our platform we needed to
basically retrain the model because the
model just didn't even work according to
the new data that i saw
that seems like there is an urgency
problem there where you detect some sort
of data drift and your model accuracy is
degrading and you really need to respond
to that really quickly
training a model might take a while so
what are some backstops that you might
have to
say stick with the accuracy maybe or
segment your users in a way where
you get the same accuracy and in the
example that you were talking about are
there strategies to deal with uh to
respond really quickly in the mlaps life
cycle that lets you
rapidly release something rapidly
release a fix rapidly say cut off access
to some data maybe that might be
corrupting your model i think it depends
on
a few different factors so one would be
in our case
we
had a very static model creation
system
the models would would basically be re
retrained every night so it wasn't super
sophisticated i mean back again 2013 was
like the stone age of of some of the
stuff that's happening with mlabs but we
would recreate a new model every night
but when you have a version model you
can always just go back in time and and
use a previous model that would have
been more accurate the other thing you
could do
is don't use
the newer model
or don't
make decisions on the newer model so
it sort of kind of stay with the older
model so for example in our situation
the reason why the model
was so important was we used it to pay
people and so we were essentially
figuring out who would be
successful and it was actually a way to
bypass traditional advertising
to grow our platform in fact it was very
effective you know a lot of people waste
a lot of money on buying
ads on their platform
you know to do user growth but we
actually just went struck straight to
influencers figured out how much we
should pay them and then had them create
content for a platform
and
in that scenario once we got into
a very new set of users where there was
really our model didn't understand yet
how to interact with them
probably
the best way to approach that would be
to not let the model make any
predictions
but to do more of like a naive forecast
so you could just say look
you know i'm going to pay you
i don't know 500
versus
i'm gonna try to predict what to pay you
you just pay somebody like a flat rate
that's like
maybe the average you pay
all of the people
that you're paying so that you can
collect some data so
in that kind of scenario
you know i think that's that's important
to not get too confident like oh great
we have this model that's working so
amazing and then all of a sudden you get
new signals that that you really don't
know how to interpret yet
especially if there's money involved or
human life involved it may be better to
just do a very cautious approach which
is again like hey we'll
we'll give you just this fixed amount of
money to see what happens and then and
then later maybe a year later you can
actually create a model so i think that
that might be the way that i would
approach
one of those kinds of problems is use an
old model and then don't make
decisions on the new data yet until you
have more data
with respect to just testing and
deployment a b testing is like a popular
way to
deploy
new features into
your production users when it comes to
machine learning do you have similar
patterns i know what you just described
is a form of like say a b testing
arguably like you have one out there and
the other one you're just observing how
it does but are there other strategies
for testing to see how well models are
going to behave as you make changes to
it i mean i think the a b testing
strategy is a pretty good strategy i
mean you could also do a percentage
though too you could do an a b testing
where the weight of the new model is
very low which i think if there's money
or human life at stake then that might
be a good strategy right is is like why
why rush into things
maybe what you do is you just throw
you know two or three or four models out
and maybe the primary model still is at
95 and then there's four other models
that are one percent of the traffic and
you just collect the data to see how
it's performing and then if one of them
does appear over time to be an
improvement and you're able to you know
figure out why it's it's an improvement
then you can promote that model and then
degrade the other models
invent your future at caci a national
security company revolutionizing
technology through digital
c4isr cyber
space engineering and i.t
transformations
you'll deliver information dominance
through the development of next
generation solutions at caci you'll be
treated like the company's greatest
asset when a company believes their
people are their greatest asset they let
the fest do what they do best
visit
careers.caci.com innovate to explore
caci's engineering and it opportunities
so let's talk a little bit about failure
handling right so when you look at
machine learning applications they're
built on various layers of foundational
services you have your data ops you have
your platform ops in what ways can you
see failures of course you can see
failures in each of those layers but how
do you respond to those failures how do
you keep your model up and running and
is there a way to tell just a failure of
something downstream from failure of
models prediction itself
one thing to consider is that many
people don't
treat data science or machine learning
like data science there's like a meta
data science layer which is kind of
surprising right is if you are deploying
something into production
and you're looking at the data there's a
word for this it's called data science
right like if you're if you're a
software engineer and you have log files
and you're using the logs to look at
statistical decisions about what you're
doing that is data science there's no
other way to put put it but monitoring
logging instrumentation is data science
so i would say that you need to also add
a meta layer
apply data science to what it is you're
doing
at each layer look at it have dashboards
that can show
the differences so so i think that's
just a no-brainer that again if you only
have experience with jupiter notebooks
this may be new to you that people have
been
looking at logs for decades i mean in
fact multiple decades this is one a
classic
problem pre-internet even people were
looking at logs and kind of sorting data
and things like that and even in like
news groups where a bulletin board
service a bbs
you know i was on those when i was in
junior high actually like when i was
like 10 i was on like you know
text-based terminals people are looking
at log files so i would say data science
is definitely
the approach to use for this
and then also i think there's the
business side which would be kind of
high level
which is you know if you deploy a model
into a production
are you actually looking at what's
happening and i think a really good
example of this actually
is social media and i i think this is a
hopefully researchers will really dig
into this more i've seen some some great
stuff about this but
this concept of the recommendation
engine is i think a perfect example of
this where you know this was a big deal
for a long time yes recommendation
engines we love recommendation engines
and one of the things i think that has
really been a problem with
recommendation engines is we're starting
to now realize that
there are unintended consequences of a
recommendation engine
and many of them are very bad right so
there is harm to
society you know
getting people harmful information and
recommending it to them because it
increases engagement so i think those
are things that are really important to
look at
from a stakeholder perspective and you
can see there's some company structures
like court b structure where they talk
about this like what is your impact on
societal you know cohesion
i think those are some things that
should be looked at like you know how
much revenue is your model making
is it actually
doing things that are helpful to you
people is it harming humans at scale
is it really something we even need to
do like i mean i think you could make
the argument that many companies that do
do recommendations of scale youtube
facebook you know those twitter that you
could even make the argument like maybe
they should turn off all recommendations
right like are they actually do we
really know
the impact
on those so i think that's another thing
to just put into the into the situation
is is once the model's been deployed
should you be prepared to just turn it
off because it's not having on one level
a surface level may be performing the
way you expect but actually what if it's
not doing what you expected at a like a
more holistic level
and what can you do to mitigate that
i think that's a really good point about
just responsible ai or ethical ai that's
being talked about right now so if you
look at ml ops as something similar to
software development you have a life
cycle of software development maybe you
know waterfall agile whatever you're
doing and you have a way of doing ml ops
at what point at what stages do you
consciously think about say the ethical
considerations of what you're trying to
build in this whole like life cycle of
building a machine learning application
for me personally one of the things i'm
trying to promote is the concept of are
you harming humans at scale
are you neutral or are you helping
humans at scale
and that's the framework i think that is
pretty straightforward right is and if
we look at
uh social media companies and i think
there there's a big documentary about
this the social dilemma
that youtube had at one point
served out more traffic to alex jones
than all of the major newspapers in the
world right i mean that to me is very
clear that's harming humans at scale and
they made a lot of money based on
putting ads on that
i hope someday there's a reckoning for
that
and you know similarly with companies
like facebook you know they're still to
this day we we don't know all the
different things they're doing but
recommending i think during the january
6th
riot or around then i don't remember all
the details but that they were actually
recommending like body armor and weapons
to people you know and we obviously see
from recent events that people do
actually act on those things they buy
body armor weapons and and do things so
there's like like not like a theoretical
connecting the dots but there's a actual
connecting of the dots i think
that would be something i hope
new people
to the industry who are talented
look at is ask yourself that question am
i
am i neutral am i harming humans of
scale or am i helping them and i think
there's this belief that
you don't have to care about that for
some reason there's certain segments of
the tech industry i don't understand why
you think you don't need to know about
this because it's the world you live in
and i think it is important for people
to say
you know i want to be careful about what
it is i'm working on i mean there's
here's a good example let's take a
company like coursera which i do a lot
of work with
they're a corp b certified company
please tell me some something they're
doing that's harming humans
or even even neutral even they're
definitely not neutral and they're
definitely not harming humans they're
helping humans at scale right that's a
pretty clear example like you're
teaching people new things that help
them you know make make more money and
it's free right like you can audit
coursera for free like i mean that's
unambiguously good
and then you can also find examples like
you know i don't know making
dirty bombs
that get put into land mines or
something like that's unambiguously bad
like like you're you're hurting people
so i think that's really something i
hope more people look at it and and not
push into like a political you know
republican democrat whatever viewpoint
because it's it's not it's a it's a fact
either you're helping you're neutral or
you're harming and i think that
framework is a good framework to
consider
yeah i want to switch gears a little bit
into just running machine learning
models in production so what does the
runtime look like for machine learning
if you're say a small company versus
a very large company what are the
options for where you can run machine
learning models and how does that impact
your revenue maybe or how quick you can
run how quickly you can iterate etc yeah
i think this is a good question you
bring up because
just like how if you were going to build
maybe a house it would be a different
tool chain than if you were going to
build a major
a skyscraper right or a condominium
tower you
would potentially have very different
machinery
or if you're going to build a bike shed
in your backyard
maybe you don't need any tools you just
need like i don't know like something
you bought a shed and you just literally
plop it down
i think that is important for companies
to think about is before you start
copying the practices of
let's say google or some large company
to really consider do you need to do the
things that the big company are doing or
in the case of a smaller company it
might be better for you to use a
pre-trained model right there's tons of
pre-trained models
and it would just not be possible for
you to get the same level of results and
maybe the pre-trained model is exactly
what you need so why not start there or
auto ml would be another one if you're
more of a medium-sized company
then potentially
you know i would maybe start to
recommend heavily looking at
using a platform people in your your
organization's certified on the platform
and organizing your workflow around the
platform and then if you're you know a
very large company you know like a top
five company or something like this
that's when they start to develop their
own infrastructure where
the core infrastructure that a medium
company would use
may not work and you'll see like a lot
of technology platforms
get developed by people
who are at one of these companies where
they have their own data center so they
can't use aws for example and so then
they build their own infrastructure so
you could probably break things into
those three different categories
and if you're a small company maybe you
just said automl can you talk more about
auto ml yeah so auto mel really the idea
here is that you're using high level
tools to train a model a bespoke model
and you know there's a lot of variation
in how much automl is actually
fully doing the job for you but
because it could kind of mean lots of
different things but in general the
concept is you take your data you feed
it into a high-level system you tell it
what target you want to predict and then
you run something you click a button
and it plugs away at the problem and
then gives you back a model
so
you know in that sense automl
i think can be a very good solution for
many organizations and and there does
appear to be
traction
with auto ml from every single platform
one of my favorite automotive solutions
is actually from apple
and it's called crate ml
in your book you talk about another
thing called kaizen ml in contrasting
with principles of kaizen so what is
kaizen ml how do you practice it yeah so
basically my point in bringing up kaizen
ml is that you know i think it's easy to
get distracted with and people even get
upset when you talk about auto mail it's
like oh you know
you're going to automate my job and
people get really worried because what
they do with kaggle they really like and
then they enjoy it but but my point is
that like kaizen ml would be more of
thinking holistically like look
we're going to automate every possible
thing that is automatable
it could be hyperparameter tuning it
could be
the trying different kinds of
experiments
but the idea is you're not
really caring
necessarily what the approach is
it could be a whole group of different
techniques but you'll use the thing that
helps you automate
as much as possible to get to the in
solution
okay
and just in terms of just bootstrapping
some sort of a machine learning solution
i think there are two approaches one is
you do it data centric way or maybe you
start with a model in mind and you do it
in a model-centric way can you talk
about what the differences are starting
one versus the other and how it might be
advantageous for say a small shop versus
like a large shop that should do it
completely differently you know it's
interesting because the data centric
versus model centric argument is
i don't know if i buy that actually so i
i think more in terms of
the rule of 25
where
to me it feels like
you may be overestimating
the organization's ability to do devops
and you also may be overestimating your
organization's ability to do product
management
and so
i think a better approach versus model
versus data centric is that all those
four quadrants are equally treated so
you know for example you have to do
maybe a maturity analysis
and look at you know at the beginning
and say look do we even have devops if
you don't who cares about model centric
or data centric you're going to fail
right
and then then look at the data like do
we have any kind of data automation well
we don't well then you'll fail and then
once once you have some of those
foundational pieces
then the other part is even if you want
to be more data centric or more model
centric and there's pros and cons to
both
still if you're not identifying the
correct business use case you also will
fail so that's why i mean
my view is a very different view than
like an expert like andrew yang who you
know is obviously you know very talented
person right and has all kinds of
experience but more in the academic
world where my experiences is like more
blue collar in that and that life spent
a lot of my life with you know greasy
hands right i'm like in the car you know
i'm building software solutions that i i
think that that delineation between
model centric and data centric
is kind of theoretically interesting for
a certain life cycle stage
but i would say that's not the place to
start the place to start would be to
holistically look at the problem which
is again the rule 25
once you have that set up and you have
all those components set up and you you
really have that feedback loop
then i could see someone making the
argument that which i don't disagree
with which is what's more important the
modeling or the data yeah probably the
data right because the modeling i can
just click a button and i can train
models so why do i need to do that let's
get even better at massaging the data i
just feel like it's it's kind of
misleading to lead with that
you know when the holistic approach i
think is where probably people should
start
and let's say you are taking a holistic
approach to starting out one of the
choices that you might have is maybe you
should be running this in the cloud by
using maybe an auto mr-like solution or
maybe just because you want to have more
compute power how do you decide whether
that's kind of like the right approach
compared to
trying to do it on-prem because your
data might be in different places is
that still a concern when you're trying
to look at it holistically to decide
where you want to do your training or
deployment and at what point you
actually like have that clarity to say
one or the other i think
that
it would potentially be a good idea to
use
the most popular solutions so let's just
take from a data science perspective
who is the the top cloud provider well
it's aws
okay well what is their product they
recommend sagemaker okay start there
right like that's one really simple way
to work and then what is the document
like literally the manual like this is
when i was
growing up this is the thing that people
used to say to you before there was
stack overflow they would say you know
rtfm you know read the manual
you know with a little bit of custom in
there and basically it's like that's
exactly what i recommend is use the
largest platform on the largest cloud
and then just literally read their
documentation and do exactly what they
say
that's probably one of the better
approaches
i think i would be a little worried
about on-prem
and dealing with that
i would probably recommend to somebody
why don't you pick the smallest possible
thing you can do that's not on-prem
initially unless you really have deep
expertise in like on-prem and you're
experts that you're doing world-class
data engineering then maybe yeah it
doesn't matter you can do anything
you'll be successful but if you're kind
of new and things are a little bit
clunky maybe just take a very very very
tiny problem like the smallest possible
problem even so a problem that's so tiny
that it it's inconsequential whether it
succeeds or fails and then get like a
pipeline working in the end again using
the most popular tools and the reason i
also mentioned the most popular tools is
that it's easy to hire people now so you
just go and say like whatever the most
popular maybe in 10 years aws won't be
the most popular i would again say pick
whatever the most popular tool is
because the documentation will be there
and it's easy to hire people
what do you have to say about the
interoperability concerns you talk about
it a little bit in the book about how
critical that is so maybe can you
explain why it's critical and let's say
you actually pick the most popular tool
chain available what do you have to do
to make sure it is interoperable in the
future i think sometimes you don't care
it's a good problem to have is that
you're successful and you're locked into
the cloud
i mean i'm not a believer in lock-in
fears
i know many people are afraid of the
lock-in but
i think a bigger problem is does
anything work that's probably the number
one problem is does anything work and i
would say maybe you know you don't need
it like you don't need to care about in
the short term
first try to make sure you get something
that works there's an expression i use
yagni you ain't gonna need it like i
think a lot of times just get something
working and see what happens and
if you need to change maybe the future
has changed at that point
and you just do the new thing
yeah that makes sense and adding on to
that i think there are some
recommendations saying go with the
microservices-based approach
and if you ask a traditional software
engineer maybe there is some more
skepticism at going with microservices
just because of the complexity but i
think you make an argument in the book
in several pieces how it might simplify
things for machine learning so can you
talk a little bit about why you think it
might simplify things and especially in
machine learning applications versus
like traditional software yeah i think
that you know traditional object
oriented monolithic kind of workflow
is really good for things like
let's say a mobile app right that could
be a great example or a content
management or payroll system or you know
something like that where there's a lot
of reasons why
maybe a monolithic application would
work very well and heavy heavy
object-oriented programming would work
very well but i think in terms of the
devops style one of the recommendations
is microservices because you can build
things very quickly and test out those
ideas and also microservices in some
sense
kind of implicitly
will use containers it's very difficult
to pull out the idea of a container from
a microservice and then the nice thing
about a container is it has the runtime
along with the software so i think the
benefits
are so great
that it's hard to ignore microservices i
mean the ability to package the runtime
alongside with the software and make a
very small change test it out and deploy
it really works well for machine
learning
when it comes to using data for your
machine learning really like data is at
the center of
your application in many ways you have
to be careful about how you use it
because there are so many regulatory
restrictions around how you use it or
there's governance around like
what you can use what you cannot use
right to forget etc so
how do you go about approaching those
limitations or
rather
regulations that you really have to like
follow legally
yeah i mean that just really depends on
the size of the organization the problem
they're solving
and also the jurisdiction that they're
in
i don't think there's a one size fits
all solution there
you know you could make an argument
that many companies collect too much
data so that's one way to solve the
problem is just don't collect it right
like there may be no good reason to
collect
you know for example if if you're using
a dating app
maybe you don't need to store the data
of the location of the users like why
why would you need that it can only
cause problems for people in the future
like again harming humans at scale so
just don't do it another thing is
maybe you don't enter certain spaces
that are heavily regulated you just
don't i don't know get into a place
where you have to
deal with that kind of regulation
another one is also the type of data so
you could just not store ever as a
practice any personally identifiable
information pii
so i think there's mitigation strategies
and part of it could just be being a lot
more careful
about what it is you collect
and or what markets you choose to get
into i think also this concept of
being a unicorn or being like a trillion
dollar company or you know i think
hopefully those days are over that
everybody wants to be a billionaire
company maybe it's okay to be a 10
million dollar company and so
maybe instead
you focus on less things
and the things you do do you do really
well and you don't care about becoming
you know some huge company and so maybe
that's another solution as well
yeah well i guess more data more
problems
but can you talk about security like are
there
specific things that you would do to
make sure that your model is secure or
something different that you wouldn't
otherwise do in traditional software
that you have to do with machine
learning or you don't have to do in
machine learning yeah i think a couple
things that come to mind is that
you know if you're training your model
on
data that the public gives you
that could be dangerous and in fact i
was at tesla headquarters
in i think it was
october so like maybe six to nine months
ago for their ai day and that was
actually a question that was asked
was what happens
maybe i asked it i don't i don't
remember but it was me or somebody like
hey well
are you sure people aren't embedding
stuff inside of your computer vision
model that causes problems
and so the answer is they said we don't
know
and i mean basically and in fact they
knew that like if you walked in front of
like a tesla and you had
the word stop on your shirt or something
like that you could like cause it to
like stop suddenly so i think that is an
area of concern which is
if you know maybe again back to the data
collection is be very careful training a
model on data that was publicly
put into the system because
if you don't have control over it
somebody could be planting a back door
into your system and just
basically creating a zero day exploit
for your system so one solution could be
especially if you're a smaller company
is just use pre-trained models
right and actually focus on
pre-trained models that have a very good
history of
data governance and best practices and
you kind of like
you drift off of their wave
you know so you can leverage their
capability so there's just a couple
ideas that i had
okay and
you said you've been doing this since
like 2013 so i kind of want to like
start wrapping up
what are the big changes you've seen
since then and what are the changes that
you see going into the future in the
next like say five six years yeah i
would say the big change that i saw
in 2013
was that at the time when i was creating
models i was actually using r
even though i've done a lot of stuff
with python and i've done stuff with c
sharp or in other languages but i was
using r because
it had some really good statistical
libraries and i like the way the machine
learning libraries work just the
libraries have just massively changed
you know that's one huge change the data
collection systems like i was using
jenkins to collect data i mean
like there's things like airflow now and
you know all these really cool
sophisticated data bricks now has gotten
a lot better there's always
sophisticated systems now that do data
engineering so i would say libraries and
data and then i would see the stuff
that's happening in the future
is and also platforms so the platforms
are definitely becoming mature now they
just didn't exist before
the libraries are becoming much better
and i think also serving
is now becoming i would say 2023 is
probably where we're going to see
a huge emphasis on model serving where
we're getting a little bit now but
that's actually my focus is model
serving
and the reason why model serving i think
is so interesting is that
we don't yet have
necessarily web frameworks that are
designed
for serving machine learning models we
have people
essentially adopting
and hacking together web frameworks like
fast api or flask
you know that will kind of take a model
and put it together you see a little bit
of this like tensorflow serving is an
example i know the ml run
has some of this as well but i think
we're gonna see some really strong
software engineering best practices
around model serving that make it way
simpler and that some of the things
that you care about like model accuracy
and like lineage all the stuff will kind
of be baked into the model serving and
then i would also say automl i think
automl will be ubiquitous
yeah that would be great like just
having that access to machine learning
that you could just do at the click of a
button and see if it does something one
last thing finally how can our listeners
reach you i know you have a lot of like
writings and videos and educational
content that you put out there so how
can people reach you or get to know your
content yeah so if you just go to noaa
gift.com you can see most of the content
i publish books courses
linkedin that's the only social network
i use i don't use twitter or facebook or
instagram
and
also if you go to coursera or o'reilly
there's a lot of content that i have on
both of those platforms
excellent
noah thank you so much for coming on the
show and talking about ml ops this is
akshay manchali for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening